# Christopher J. Urban

Davie Hall Room 351 Chapel Hill, NC 27599 ☑ cjurban@live.unc.edu ③ https://cjurban.github.io/

I am a sixth year Ph.D. candidate in Quantitative Psychology at UNC-Chapel Hill. My research aims to develop and disseminate machine learning methods for social data science.

#### Education

2017–2023 (Expected)

Ph.D., Quantitative Psychology, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

Minor in Statistics and Operations Research

Advisor: Daniel Bauer

2017–2021 M.A., Quantitative Psychology, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

Advisor: Daniel Bauer

Thesis: Machine learning-based estimation and goodness-of-fit for large-scale confirmatory item

factor analysis

2012–2016 **B.S.**, *Psychology*, Stony Brook University.

Minor in Mathematics; Concentrations in Mathematics and Physics

2010–2011 A.A., Humanities and Social Sciences, Onondaga Community College.

## **Funding**

2019-Spring 2022

National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship; \$138,000

## **Publications**

#### Refereed Articles

Arizmendi, C. J., Bernacki, M. L., Rakovic, M., Plumley, R. D., **Urban, C.J.**, Panter, A. T., ... Gates, K. M. (2022). Predicting student outcomes using internet logs of learning behaviors: Review, current standards, and suggestions for future work. *Multivariate Behavioral Research*.

**Urban, C. J.** & Bauer, D. J. (2021). A deep learning algorithm for high-dimensional exploratory item factor analysis. *Psychometrika*. 86 (1), 1–29.

**Urban, C. J.** & Gates, K. M. (2021). Deep learning: A primer for psychologists. *Psychological Methods.* 26 (6), 743–773.

Greene, J. A., Plumley, R. D., **Urban, C. J.**, Bernacki, M. L., Gates, K. M., Hogan, K. A., Demetriou, C., & Panter, A. T. (2019). Modeling temporal self-regulatory processing in a higher education biology course. *Learning and Instruction*.

#### **Under Review**

Bernacki, M.L., **Urban, C.J.**, Raković, M., Plumley, R.D., Luo, L., Gates, K.M., . . . Greene, J.A. (under review). Leveraging learning analytics to support postsecondary students equitably. *American Educational Research Journal*.

### **Book Chapters**

Arizmendi, C. J., **Urban, C. J.** & Gates, K. M. (in press). Deep learning methods for mobile sensing. In Mehl, M. R., Eid, M., Wrzus, C., Harari, G. M., & Ebner-Priemer, U. W. (Eds.), *Mobile Sensing in Psychology: Methods and Applications*. Guilford Press.

Eaton, N. R. & **Urban, C. J.** (2018). Parental monitoring. In *Encyclopedia of Adolescence* (2nd ed., pp. 2666–2679). Springer.

## Statistical Software

**Urban, C. J.** & He, S. (2022). DeepIRTools: Deep learning-based estimation and inference for large-scale item response theory. Python package. https://github.com/cjurban/deepirtools

## Professional Experience

2022-Present

Statistical Consultant, Department of Psychology and Neuroscience, UNC-Chapel Hill.

- Provide consulting services to social scientists including discussion of research goals, planning for data collection, and guidance on implementation and interpretation of statistical models
- 2018–2019 Research Assistant, The Finish Line Project, UNC-Chapel Hill.
  - o Developed a machine learning model for predicting student performance in a large undergraduate course, then deployed the model to intervene for at-risk students
- Summer 2018
- Research Assistant, Department of Psychology and Neuroscience, UNC-Chapel Hill.
- o Investigated methods for clustering individuals using brain network connectivity patterns

# Teaching Experience

October 2022

**Instructor**, *The Methods Center at the Faculty of Economics and Social Sciences*, Eberhard Karl University of Tübingen.

Workshop Title: Foundations of Deep Learning for the Social Sciences

Website: https://cjurban.github.io/workshops/deep\_learning\_social\_sciences/intro.html

- Prepared and instructed a two-day workshop designed to introduce foundational deep learning concepts and methods to social scientists
- Fall 2017 **Teaching Assistant**, Department of Psychology and Neuroscience, UNC-Chapel Hill. Course Title: Statistical Principles in Psychological Research
  - Developed and led exercises to teach basic statistical methods for data analysis

#### Invited Talks

- October 2021 **Urban, C. J.** Deep learning and psychometrics: A fruitful new synthesis. Virtual talk given at the Methods Center in the Faculty of Economics and Social Sciences at Eberhard Karl University of Tübingen, Tübingen, Germany.
- October 2021 **Urban, C. J.** Deep learning and psychometrics: A fruitful new synthesis. Virtual talk given at the QuantDev Brownbag in the College of Health and Human Development at The Pennsylvania State University, University Park, PA.
- September 2021 **Urban, C. J.** Deep learning and psychometrics: A fruitful new synthesis. Virtual talk given at the Quantitative Methods Colloquium Series in the Department of Psychology and Human Development at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN.

#### Awards & Honors

- April 2019 Trainee Travel Award, BRAIN Initiative Investigator's Meeting; \$1,000
- May 2018 Society of Multivariate Experimental Psychology Workshop Travel Award; \$1,000
- 2012–2016 Stony Brook University Dean's List
- 2010–2011 Onondaga Community College President's List

#### Service

- 2022 **Reviewer**, Multivariate Behavioral Research.
- 2022 **Reviewer**, Psychometrika.
- 2021 **Student Coordinator**, Quantitative Psychology Forum, UNC-Chapel Hill.
- 2020–2021 **Reviewer**, British Journal of Mathematical and Statistical Psychology.
  - 2021 **Reviewer**, Journal of Social and Personal Relationships.

# Conference Papers and Presentations

- April 2020 Bernacki, M. L., **Urban, C. J.**, Plumley, R., Luo, L., Gates, K., Panter, A., & Greene, J. A. Leveraging campus data, learning theory, and educational data mining to predict achievement before students begin to fail. Poster presented at the annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, San Francisco, CA. (Conference cancelled)
- April 2019 **Urban, C. J.**, Fisher, Z. F., Parsons, J., Girault, J. B., Hopfinger, J. B., & Gates, K. M. *Classifying individuals based on within-network connectivity.* Poster presented at the BRAIN Initiative Investigator's Meeting, Washington, DC.
- April 2019 Girault, J. B., Arizmendi, C., Fisher, Z. F., **Urban, C. J.**, Piven, J., & Gates, K. M. *Identifying age-related functional connectivity features across different levels of spatial resolution: An application of multi-scale GIMME*. Poster presented at the BRAIN Initiative Investigator's Meeting, Washington, DC.
- April 2019 Greene, J. A., **Urban, C. J.**, Plumley, R. D., Bernacki, M. L., Gates, K. M., Hogan, K. A., Demetriou, C., & Panter, A. T. *Theory-driven data mining to understand self-regulated learning processing in a higher education biology course.* Paper presented at the annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, Toronto, Canada.
- May 2018 **Urban, C. J.**, Bernacki, M. L., Plumley, R. D., Gates, K. M., Demetriou, C., Panter, A. T., Hogan, K. A., & Greene, J. A. *A supervised data mining approach for identifying behavior sequences related to academic performance*. Poster presented at the Modern Modeling Methods Conference, Storrs, CT.
- November 2015 Taggart, T. C., **Urban, C. J.**, Reisner, S. L., & Eaton, N. R. *Correlates of sexual attraction and behavior with transgender individuals*. Poster presented at the annual meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Sexuality, Albuquerque, NM.